<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-08-14T01:08:39+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">The Symptomatic Case Of The Survey Paper</title><link href="/2023/08/13/The-Symptomatic-Case-Of-The-Survey-Paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Symptomatic Case Of The Survey Paper" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/The-Symptomatic-Case-Of-The-Survey-Paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/The-Symptomatic-Case-Of-The-Survey-Paper.html"><![CDATA[<p>If there is one thing that can be said about written communication in the academic world, it is its high degree of codification.
Communication can take various forms, and while its type largely depends on the domain of research, it usually falls under one of the following generic options:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Short papers (that are often accompanied by a poster) are good vectors for presenting initial results or exposing a problem; they tend to be 	not definitive piece of work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Conference papers typically focus on addressing a well-defined and specific problem through the presentation of a solution to that problem and an assessment of its benefits.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Journal papers are denser, deeper, and more mature pieces of work. They can be the result of several months/years of work and present an in-depth vision that significantly contributes to advancing the state-of-the art.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Magazine 	papers are in general less technical, more accessible (in terms of 	content) and designed to be read more rapidly. They aim at presenting an overview of a problem space or a vision.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Besides their format, written communications also vary in terms of the nature of the reported content: to shed the light on an emergent/important/pressing issue in order to encourage further discussion and future research, to detail pros and cons of a new solution, to justify novel design choices and demonstrate their benefits (qualitative and quantitative), to give an overview of a domain and highlight its past, present and future, etc. The latter is often referred to as survey.
In practice, while the type of communication should be driven by the nature of the work to report, it is not rare for one to shape the actual work to meet the requirements of a specific format. In fact, and that can be very afflicting, the selected format is also very often driven by the prestige provided by a specific type of communication.
Every type of paper has its inherent difficulty. Writing a (good) scientific paper is a pretty hard task. It is far from just being a compilation of subject-verb-complement sentences. It needs a structure. It needs a depth. It needs style. And it needs to coherently convey complicated stuff.
There is however something that I find quite symptomatic about the case of survey papers in that these papers tend to be – very often – bad papers.
It would definitely deserve a whole article to really explain what a good vs. a bad paper is. But in a nutshell, my definition of a good paper is a paper that teaches me something and / or opens up my perspective. In contrast, a bad paper is dull, boring, and contributes very little to enriching one’s knowledge. Please note that I am not talking about style here but about structure and content.
I don’t want to discourage anyone who has been engaging in the development of a survey. I think however that it needs to be clear for everyone that writing a good survey paper is going to be tough. It might be because the task is so demanding (if properly carried out) that in 99% of the cases produced survey papers are literally no more than nice keyword-based filters implemented on Google Scholar (or Scopus or Web of Science).
Yes, to survey does imply filtering and categorising information, but specifically in the case of research surveys, it is only one part. What makes a survey truly interesting is the depiction of how a research question or a domain has been evolving through produced knowledge. In that sense, survey work is by nature subjective. It reflects one’s vision of this evolution.
A reason why I often get upset about survey papers, and their review, and their publication, is because these papers can attract a lot of citations. And when (unfortunately) the number of citations ends up being used as an indicator of the importance of a research, it becomes an issue.
A good survey provides a point of view that is informed by experience (browsing through a paper and writing its summary does not qualify). It necessitates distance and general knowledge (taking for granted what three academics say is not sufficient). A large number of survey papers consists in groupings of sequentially enumerated references. In the best case, the referenced work comes with a vague (and often inaccurate) one-sentence description of its content. In the majority of the cases, however, the work is simply numbered.
In my opinion, the added-value of these types of survey papers comes from nothing more than the static implementation of a filter function on Google Scholar. “Relevant” material is searched by keywords for the sole purpose of the survey. The paper sometimes explains how these keywords were selected, and provides some statistics on the obtained results, which I assume is to convey a form of principled approach in how the survey was compiled. I am not saying that these results are completely useless. In fact they could be very useful as guidelines for developing open-source research paper filter tools, for instance. But for the sake of presenting a vision, these contributions are pretty much void.
This is a very personal opinion here but I believe that the survey paper market is today driven by major forces. Because these types of papers tend to attract a lot of citations, they are regarded as fantastic leverage by some academics. And the sad thing is that in many cases, these academics are likely not to be largely involved in the preparation of the survey. These papers are very often written by PhD researchers, who can also be very junior in a field.
In fact, I would also argue that we may also see in this pattern a manifestation of an endemic problem in academia: there are countless PhD researchers left without any proper supervision and who, in the absence of guidance, can find comfort in accumulating readings. Far from me the idea of blaming PhD candidates, I went through that, with almost absent supervision from my official supervisor (I was saved by my unofficial second-supervisor, a person to whom I forever owed what I became as an academic, and who saved me from writing a survey). There is nothing worse than uncertainty to destroy self-confidence. After spending 9-10 months of their first year reading mountains of papers, and by then starting to grasp the mechanics of a self-contented research, PhD researchers can easily be confirmed in their own conviction that there is a value in that reading and that it would be good to share it with the rest of the community. The problem is that this reading is often not backed by any clear understanding of a specific problem, which very much reflects in how the survey is constructed: except a long list of references that the PhD researcher tried to categorise for his/her own good, there is nothing very interesting said in the sruvey.
So I know, I may sound harsh. There are some good surveys out there, and there are also PhD researchers who can write very good surveys. My point is that they are rare, and that things really deserve to be improved.
But who to blame for the lack of good surveys? Certainly not the PhD researchers. In fact I can often perceive exploitation and lack of concern from the academics listed on the top right of the paper through these papers. The supervisor? Certainly to some extent. As supervisor of less experienced researchers, our moral duty is to help them build confidence, help them develop a vision. But are only the supervisors the ones to blame? What about journals and magazines that accept these types of work for publication? Of course for them, it is good business since it increases their visibility and influence (see the impact factor). And what about reviewers? Can we as reviewers honestly claim that we learn so much from the listing of 167 references?
So is the conclusion not to write any survey? I am convinced that good surveys are very valuable to research, to the community and to knowledge. A good survey provides a unique vision to a long term problem. It contributes to the intelligence of the domain: to a work of thinking and structuration. I will explore in detail in a subsequent article what I believe is needed to write a good survey. For the time being, let’s be honest, and let’s just not publish useless filter-type papers.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If there is one thing that can be said about written communication in the academic world, it is its high degree of codification. Communication can take various forms, and while its type largely depends on the domain of research, it usually falls under one of the following generic options:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Competitive Environment</title><link href="/2023/08/13/A-Competitive-environment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Competitive Environment" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/A-Competitive-environment</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/A-Competitive-environment.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-competitive-environment">A competitive environment</h1>

<p>There are a lot more PhD students than the number of academic positions available.
According to a report from the Higher Education Policy institute in the UK (HEPI), 67% of PhD students want a career in academic research but only 30% stay in academia three years on. 
These numbers mean that most young researchers are not able to achieve their career objectives after many years of sustained effort and sacrifice. This is a tragic situation for many early career researchers that find themselves having to forgo their dreams of conducting ground breaking research for the benefit of humanity.
In this article our objective is not to establish the reasons why there are too many PhD students for the amount of positions available, for that we refer the reader to this good nature careers podcast titled “too many PhDs too few research positions” where one of the participants compares the situation to a failure at “birth control”. Instead we are looking at the implications of the increased competition on the researchers and the actions they are then led to take to keep their dreams alive.</p>

<h2 id="a-rat-race-for-the-young-researcher">A rat race for the young researcher</h2>
<p>As the HEPI report cited previously suggests, most PhD students intended a career in academia after the completion of their degree. However, the struggle to build an academic career is so persistent that is has become a popular theme in many Hollywood movies that portray researchers. It is often represented as a tension between the researcher’s independence in how they live their life or express their ideas and the obtention of a tenure which would allow them job security and intellectual freedom. Unfortunately, in this case fiction and reality are very similar.
Studying for a PhD is training to become a researcher. Given this fact, one would assume that the career path of a young academic should look like this : Complete PhD -&gt; Get an academic position -&gt; Build an expertise and reputation -&gt; become professor -&gt; Retire.
In reality, getting to professorship feels more like an asymptote that can never be reached, most early career researchers get stuck building an expertise and a reputation and searching for the next contract that will keep them employed for the next 6-18months. And of course on top of that researchers are encouraged to “move around” between institutions so they can build their networks and boost their employability, completely ignoring that some of them have dependents of aspire to settle.  It is common to remain in this loop over a decade before finally giving up, which is an indication that the 30% cited in the report remaining after 3 years are only the early leavers.</p>

<h2 id="an-international-competition">An international competition</h2>
<p>One of the best features of the academic world is its diversity, people from all around the world meeting to exchange ideas and learn from one another. Working in academia will expose you to a plurality of cultures, languages which greatly challenge and enrich your experience and understanding of the world. The downside though, is that as a market participant in this industry, the competition seems fiercer than ever before and it’s become rather difficult for an individual researcher to differentiate themselves from their peers. A lot of the metrics traditionally used to assess one’s research output are being gamified. For example, the number of publications and impact factor are two metrics that together should represent your ability to produce new ideas and assess the impact of those ideas on your field. Unfortunately, these metrics can completely be overtaken by “gangs” that will add and cite each other on their publications in order to improve their score and look more appealing to funding bodies and other universities.  A consequence of this is also the flood of articles with questionable results that dilutes the quality of the scientific literature. Sadly, there are no standardisation body/regulator to even the playing field for everyone.</p>

<h2 id="the-rise-of-the-science-influencer">The rise of the science influencer</h2>

<p>Given  the difficulty faced by young researchers to shine through conventional metrics such as research publication count/quality and impact factor, they are now increasingly using other means of signalling, meaning unconventional means to stand out amongst their peers and build a successful career. This often means an increased social media presence to disseminate their work and demonstrate their expertise in a given subject matter or participation in outreach events to build a public presence that could propel their careers. 
At face value this seems to be a positive development that should be encouraged as it participates in the promotion of research and raises awareness of scientific topics. However the question we ask is what is the cost of this new behaviour on the quality of the research produced and disseminated within the scientific community and the broader public? Additionally, what is the cost on the health of young researchers subjected to yet another source of pressure to produce output? “Publish or Perish” was the mantra of early career researchers, instilling a constant feeling of anxiety over one’s ability to constantly produce new ideas that will be deemed worthy by peers. The new mantra is slowly shaping up to be “Publish, maintain a Twitter/Linkedin/Facebook/Youtube profile or perish”. This once again is yet another role that is added to the responsibilities of researchers, that of outreach officer. <br />
Given that there are still only 24 hours in a day, there is inevitably a threshold of diminishing returns that will be crossed where any new hat worn by a researcher is negatively impacting the quality of their research output.</p>

<h2 id="the-industry-exit">The industry exit</h2>

<p>Moving from academia to industry is often the route taken by researchers after many years of holding on to their dream of finally being able to do the research they want, sometimes at the expense of a comfortable life. It is often seen by researchers themselves as a personal failure, a capitulation versus money, something so meaningless relative to their initial ambition. Fortunately many go on to have brilliant careers in industry and find other ways to drive change. Universities are also becoming aware of the need for coaching young researchers that find themselves needing to transition to industry. Coaching programmes are not widespread yet but where they do exist, they provide the support and guidance necessary for researchers leaving the academic world to understand what are their transferable skills and how to translate their many talents in a language more familiar to the traditional jobs market. Universities seem to still struggle to understand why investing in the staff leaving their institutions is beneficial to them. If we could suggest one reason, it’d be that the staff leaving on good terms is more likely to maintain a good relationship with their former institution and build pathways to industry partnerships. This is how industry partnerships could be born and research further enhanced for the benefit of all those involved and the broader public.</p>

<h2 id="the-spinout-route">The spinout route</h2>

<p>Faced with the harsh reality of the lack of academic positions and the scarcity of research funds, researchers often venture to more exotic pools of money in an attempt to bring their vision to life. Starting a company based on their research often sounds like an appealing solution, killing two birds with one stone. First this opens access to funds that were previously unavailable and that have much deeper liquidity than any conventional research funding body can provide. Second, it makes you more attractive to your own institution and more likely to land a permanent academic position. Of course there is also the possibility to get rich beyond your wildest dreams. 
This route is now highly encouraged by universities seeking to generate impact by commercialising their IP and creating new income streams and supported by governments chasing ever more economic growth and competitiveness for their economy in a global market.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>As a short conclusion, the profession of researcher is now highly competitive, which leads early career researchers to seek ways to be creative to differentiate themselves and build fulfilling careers. The routes taken by young researchers to make a living could be argued to lead to less desirable outcomes for research since the additional distractions surrounding their core activity are diluting the long and slow focus required to make true groundbreaking advances.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A competitive environment]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Developing A Research Project</title><link href="/2023/08/13/Developing-A-Research-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Developing A Research Project" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/Developing-A-Research-Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/Developing-A-Research-Project.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-genesis-of-a-research-project">The genesis of a research project</h1>

<p>One of the roles of the researcher is to produce research proposals. A research proposal is usually a document presenting a new research project that a researcher is presenting to a funding body with the goal of obtaining financial support for their scientific investigation.</p>

<h2 id="part-i-top-down-research">Part I: Top down research</h2>
<p>It has become very common that a country interested in boosting its research output will create organisations dedicated to establishing research priorities and allocating funds.
For example in the UK, there is a public body called UKRI that directs research and innovation funding and conducts assessments of its funding beneficiaries through a process called REF (Research Excellence Framework). UKRI comprises 7 research councils that each have a set budget to allocate to their specific areas of interest. In this context it is interesting to consider the implications of such a method of funding allocation.</p>

<p>Note: As for many things in life, it is often easier to complain about the things that don’t work than it is to look at the positive side. In this first article on the topic, I will focus mostly on exposing the negative consequences of top down funded research, which does not mean there aren’t advantages to this. Subsequent posts will look at the positive side and alternative models.</p>

<p>How is a research project born and developed in a context where funding is administered in a top down fashion? 
Let’s take for example a researcher in a public UK research institution. Their typical approach will be to remain up to date with various calls for proposals from several funding bodies around their research topics.  With the submission deadlines in mind, the researcher will put together a research proposal that fits the big themes emphasised by the funding bodies and that will hopefully look attractive enough to the panel of experts in charge of reviewing applications. 
The review process is designed to be as fair as possible, although there are always anecdotal accounts of politics interfering with the normal process of decision making. 
Lately, calls for proposals have also come with templates for the applicants to follow with sections not related directly to the activities of research but to adjacent things such as outreach, impact on the society at large or exploitation plans (whether this should be the case or not is up for debate).</p>

<p>In this context, The exercise of writing a research proposal can roughly be one of three things.</p>
<ol>
  <li>You already have a research project that you have been developing for a while and luckily it falls within the themes proposed. In this case, you can focus your efforts in demonstrating that you have the means to deliver on this project and in evidencing why you need funding to overcome a specific hurdle. Additionally, you must show that given your rich expertise, you are well suited to conduct this work.</li>
  <li>The theme doesn’t apply directly to your research interests but you are in need of funding to develop something that you deem important enough to want to spend a consequent amount of your time working on it. In this case  the exercise is more artistic because you must find a way to elegantly fit the call for proposal to your research project.</li>
  <li>In this case, all you need is money, you are desperate for it and often, it is because your job security depends on it. What you do in this case is use your imagination, the scientific literature, the reputation of your institution, the keywords in the call for proposal, your network as project partners, anything works as long as it increases your chances of getting the money. With all that you can propose a completely new research avenue that fits the call for proposals. Unfortunately, this is often the case that applies.</li>
</ol>

<p>The first case is probably the one every researcher dreams of finding themselves into. This is the case where the proposal almost writes itself, you understand the field, you know intimately what the critical issues are and can formulate an honest plan to overcome them.  You shouldn’t struggle to support your expertise and you are in a position to evidence your proposed project with preliminary or partial results from your existing work. This is a proposal that exists in the continuity of your ongoing activities and might add a few innovative steps or even very hard challenges but the direction  and reward is more or less clear.</p>

<p>The second case is what I refer to as  the semi artistic case also called trying to fit a square peg into a round hole. This is where the research you are doing isn’t directly related to the theme of the call for proposal so you add fluff and colours to it to make it look close enough. It is research after all, so insights from one field might find applications in another one, if one only takes the time to look. You still do need to sound convincing, luckily this approach is not only used to trick the selection panel as there might genuinely be cross pollination of fields and often breakthroughs come from multi-disciplinary approaches. There you have it, your plausible deniability.</p>

<p>The third case is what happens more often than researchers will admit. There is pressure to bring funding into the department therefore researchers are made to turn into novelists. The entire exercise becomes a challenge to tell a good story and check all the boxes of the call for proposal whatever the means. You will invent a research project out of thin air, maybe helped with your expertise and then convince yourself that it has merits beyond obtaining funds so you can better defend it. You can also imagine all the benefits that society will gain from your breakthroughs and all the ways in which you will perform outreach activities. If in addition to this you can add letters of support from a few companies within your network then it goes a long way to show the strength of the proposal. Again, it is a research project so nobody can blame you for being overly optimistic.</p>

<h2 id="so-what-">So what ?</h2>
<p>An obvious flaw in this top down approach to research funding is that - as in the prevalent case 3 - researchers might be led to consider research avenues not for their personal convictions about what is important/interesting to investigate but to blindly follow the source of funds wherever it takes them, thus silencing their own expertise to the benefit of those who decide budget allocations.</p>

<h2 id="so-is-this-good-or-bad">So is this good or bad?</h2>
<p>Well, It depends on the context. In a commercial context it does make sense that an entity whose purpose is economic returns would identify what areas give it an edge and therefore push resources there to hopefully unlock many riches. Of course Governments’ obsession with GDP growth does also put them in this context but wouldn’t it be more efficient to leave this type of hands on approach to private entities? The reason being that the concept of opportunity-cost seems to apply better to a company that is driven by private profit/loss and therefore more able and incentivised to focus the efforts of its researchers to activities that will reap profits. An obvious question that might come to your mind as you are reading this is, how do we then incentivise research into big challenges that might not have an obvious financial return but still a tangible impact on our quality of life? We will touch on this in the “positives” of top down research funding but an element of response is that researchers are also people and as such they also do care about their quality of life and so do not require a mandate to be interested in making it better. 
Moreover, there needs to exist research institutions from which the research can be trusted by the taxpayers as not being biassed by the judgement of any central party despite the political preferences of the time. 
Should government funding for research exist? Yes, though, my personal conviction is that it should directly fund research institutions which themselves will fund researchers and give them the means to freely explore topics they themselves deem important, leaving open (or incentivising) the possibility of collaboration with private entities to further fund results that bear an interesting commercial potential. In this way, there will not be a preselection of winning and losing ideas by the funding bodies to the detriment of other potential breakthroughs.
And even though the selection panels for funding allocation are made of experts, let’s remember that paradigm shifts in science often happen in spite of the current established experts, not because of them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The genesis of a research project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Attending Events</title><link href="/2023/08/13/Attending-Events.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Attending Events" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/Attending-Events</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/Attending-Events.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="events-to-attend-or-not-to-attend-that-is-the-question">Events: to attend or not to attend, that is the question.</h1>

<p>Believe it or not, researchers are a social species. They are happy to go to the outside world to meet people and talk. It is one thing to sit in a lab, to close the door and to stick to a desk. It is another to have ideas mature by learning from others, and engaging in collaborations.
Events are an important component of research. They act as professional enablers to a socially active research ecosystem. Reasons to attend an event can be diverse, as is one’s financial / time / administrative ability to join these specialised meetings. <br />
In this article, I share some thoughts on what it means for a researcher to attend an event.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-exactly-mean-by-events">What do you exactly mean by events?</h2>
<p>Generally speaking events can be defined as any gatherings that aim at bringing together for a few days a bunch of people who share a common interest on a specific topic. Events fall under different types that usually depend on the audience (academics, industries, policy-makers, entrepreneurs, etc.), scope (from few attendees to thousands of participants), and objective, i.e., from expert discussions to showcase new advances to training programmes, or large scale discussions about today’s most pressing issues.<br />
As researchers, we usually aim at attending events that are related to our area of research. Of course there is in practice no objection for a researcher in aircraft engineering to attend an event focusing on drug discovery for diabetes. However, that might not be the “best” way to invest time in the context of what we research (but again it might be that research on aircraft engineering can inform research on drug discovery for diabetes, and vice versa).
The type of events that we decide to join also very often depend on our career stage. Take the example of workshops. These are traditionally small-scale gatherings (in the order of few dozens of participants) that focus on very specific and highly specialised topics (e.g., the first international workshop on the use of mRNA-messenger type message passing for securing quantum communications – note that while I admit that this is a completely made up example, there might be ongoing work in that direction). A typical setting for workshops is that of PhDs that give PhD researchers the opportunity to talk about their work early on and get feedback from senior peers in the community.
Some events can be particularly large. See the thousand+ attendees-style conferences that are annual gatherings bringing together everyone interested in a specific area of innovation to track the latest developments.
Whatever their type, events are by nature specialised meetings that people attend to enrich their professional experience.</p>

<h2 id="enriching-my-professional-experience-for-what">Enriching my professional experience for what?</h2>
<p>Motives for attendance can be quite diverse, ranging from a need to present what we do to the eagerness of getting to know what others do, or to simply pop in in order to strengthen existing or create new collaborations. 
Ultimately the reasons why we attend an event are heavily connected to our research career stage. A fresh PhD researcher will want to increase chances of exposure, while a long-term established academic will be honoured to share a long insightful experience with the community.
Events are organised in such a way that anyone can maximise chances for social interactions. These interactions can be indirect through the delivery of a speech in front of an audience (also referred to as presentation) that is traditionally followed by a Q&amp;A session. They are also encouraged more directly through coffee breaks, lunches and dinners, and so-called social activities.
In fact events are the place to be for sustaining our network, but also to either meet old folks or create new contacts.</p>

<h2 id="isnt-it-intimidating-to-stand-in-the-middle-of-a-random-bunch-of-people">Isn’t it intimidating to stand in the middle of a random bunch of people?</h2>
<p>This is definitely a very subjective appreciation, but from my personal experience we are quite a number of good souls to find the experience of participating in events, well err, an experience. 
Imagine, you get to a venue. There are hundreds of people around, some pretty well-established in their respective domain. You go to the registration desk, are given a bunch of (useless?) goodies and a label that you need to carry throughout the next few days so that people know who you are. Assuming that you are the only representative from your lab/office, you might feel awkward forcing yourself to engage in random discussions.
Having said that, researchers have generally a rather good ability for practice. The more events one attends, the more confident one is likely to become. In fact attendees who may seem over-confident might have actually worked a lot to get up to that level of eloquence in such settings. Nevertheless it can indeed be quite intimidating, especially when our personality does not match this type of things very well.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-about-strictly-sticking-to-the-event-venue">Is it about strictly sticking to the event venue?</h2>
<p>This is again quite subjective as it is really down to the perception of what work means to us. I really don’t see why one should be judgmental either against someone spending very long hours at work, or against someone who prefers working short but productive hours.
A facet of being a researcher is that it should be easy, and more importantly encouraged, to be able to embrace the perspective that best matches our own way of working. There is something fundamentally creative about doing research, and as such, it seems to me quite contradictory to set some pre-defined patterns on how one should spend time to achieve the ultimate goal of making knowledge advance.
On that account I believe we should stop this form of hypocrisy that stipulates that attending an event is not about enjoying some good time. To anticipate any attack, let me clarify my argument here: yes, attending an event is about work. The prime objective is and should always be to professionally benefit from leaving work for a few days (and also from paying bloody expensive registration fees…) to get our perspectives exposed and enriched. So if one’s objective is to get a visa to a fairy place without any intention to show one’s face in the event, there is clearly something broken in the motives.
Now events constitute a chance to travel and see something different, which is a non-negligible advantage of being a researcher. No one is going to be fully attentive to everything going on during the event (days can be quite packed), so no one should feel obliged to attend everything. Getting out and feeling the vibe of the local place can also participate in feeding our creativity.</p>

<h2 id="are-we-entering-the-era-of-online-events">Are we entering the era of online events?</h2>
<p>The ongoing covid-19 pandemic has been significantly influencing the way we work as researchers. Among the different things that have been impaired by the situation, the opportunity to physically attend events constitutes a very obvious example. The community rapidly reacted by moving a large number of events to online, virtual settings., which is also likely to have longer term consequences on how we join these events in the years to come.
On one hand online settings tend to make attendance more convenient. It is not only more affordable, it is also easier for the participants to access and arrange. On the other hand, it displaces social interactions, which in my opinion, is a crucial component in the motives behind travelling to participate in meetings, conferences, or symposiums. It is yet to be demonstrated whether virtual gatherings provide the same means as physical meetings for creating these interactions.
There is certainly space for these types of events to develop further. Future prospects might seriously impair our ability to easily travel in the years to come, and online events do offer a good alternative. In addition, they provide an opportunity for accessing at limited costs a wider spectrum of discussions, which can be highly valuable for informing our research. In addition, they may help establish new collaborative models by which research can operate by facilitating online interactions and resource (i.e., competence) consolidation.
Like so many things, it is likely that the solution to future events will come in the form of hybrid formats, where one would be able to navigate between physical and online settings. Whatever the future of these events will be, let’s not forget that the social aspect is a true driver to fulfilling a research based on trust, exchanges, and possible professional friendship.</p>

<h1 id="alright-so-conclusion-attending-or-not">Alright, so conclusion, attending or not?</h1>
<p>I remember my first participation at a research-related event. It was a small PhD workshop that was organised to give young researchers in my field the chance to interact with people in the community. It was all excitement at the time: meeting a bunch of people; traveling with my lab mates; exposing my work in front of a (critical) audience. That was all new to me.
Time has passed since then, and I often end up weighing today the pros and cons of registering to an event. I will need to arrange the trip. I will be away from home for a few days. I will need to arrange all the rest around. I did not give these things much thought in my younger research years.
Our job as researchers strives for a constant balance between many responsibilities. Each of them takes time and necessitates commitment. Events are crucial to sustaining our communication efforts. They are essential to learn and be exposed. They are essential to interact with the outside world. So it is definitely needed to accommodate times for attending events. It is also a training field for practicing skills that are often not emphasized enough for research: talking, networking and meeting.
It is up to our personality to decide which and how many events we can honestly cover a year. Up to what we also expect in our research career. There is no typical research profile.  Research is a set of things, up to us to decide where we put our priorities.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Events: to attend or not to attend, that is the question.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coping With the Literature</title><link href="/2023/08/13/Coping-With-The-Literature.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coping With the Literature" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/Coping-With-%20The-Literature</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/Coping-With-The-Literature.html"><![CDATA[<p>“The imposing edifice of science provides a challenging view of what can be achieved by the accumulation of many small efforts in a steady objective and dedicated search for truth” - Charles H. Townes</p>

<p>The primary job of a researcher is to expand the frontiers of knowledge for themselves and the wider society, using the scientific method to discover new fundamental truths about the universe that were previously unknown. In this process of continuous expansion of our common understanding of the world, researchers unlock new and more efficient ways to fight diseases, communicate or travel over long distances or to just better understand the causality of events around us.<br />
As suggested by the American physicist Charles H. Townes, our common scientific knowledge is an imposing edifice incrementally built over time in search for truth. It is a thousand years old edifice that we are still building to this day and to continue its progression, researchers must understand the existing infrastructure and add on top. Understanding the state of the art is a prerequisite to any attempt at making a meaningful contribution to any field of research but this is an increasingly difficult task to achieve. 
The reasons are multiple, the most obvious being the sheer amount of scientific  knowledge accumulated by our predecessors, the less obvious reasons are due to the terrible quality of research currently dumped into the scientific literature and incentivised by a broken model for research funding. Imagine completing a building with no plans and with load bearing walls obfuscated by hundreds of faux-pillars made with cheap plastic. That is how it feels being a researcher today.
In  this article we will expose the dynamics that many researchers will recognise after spending some time working in academia and attempt to provide clues as to why these dynamics appear and how to navigate the keeping-up-with-literature  side of being a researcher. We will also attempt to imagine a different structure for research in a way that although one still needs to put in the effort to understand the current state of the art, the faux-pillars are naturally expelled from the infrastructure in the way the scientific method was supposed to allow.</p>

<h2 id="pace-of-accumulation-of-articles">Pace of accumulation of articles</h2>

<p>Publish or perish, this is the mantra of the early career researcher. If living beings are good at one thing, it is optimising to survive for as long as possible. Researchers are living beings.
A simple directive given to millions of researchers all over the world has made the scientific literature for the most part rubbish. Some scientists talk about a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/533452a">reproducibility crisis</a> in experiment-rich fields such as biology or psychology, where 70% of scientists (from a pool of 1500) admit failing to reproduce results from the literature. This survey reveals an alarming problem with the current state of the scientific literature. 
Let’s all remember that the scientific literature should be written to improve the pool of knowledge of society as a whole. Instead, a lay person must now be trained in every possible field of science to discern for themselves what is correct from what is pure nonsense. Of course, faced with this challenge, the lay person adopts the most rational stance,  complete skepticisms accompanied with an unhealthy dose of conspiracy theories. Is global warming even real? What about 5G and Covid? Are they tracking us with the vaccines?
Before becoming an expert in any given field, one starts as a lay person. Most scientists start their career in research with a limited knowledge of their field but also with the ambition to make a lasting and meaningful contribution to science. But where do you start when the literature is so vast one cannot realistically ingest it all let alone keep track of the latest developments? In an ideal world, a PhD student would receive guidance from their supervisors on the state of the art so they can at least know where the challenges are and where to begin. In reality, their supervisors have long stopped doing any meaningful research due to overwhelming teaching and managerial responsibilities which mostly consist in finding additional funding to keep the team alive. The funding comes by showing a long track record of publications and writing research proposals containing a mix match of the current trendy key-words  “AI powered blockchain for quantum based COVID drug discovery”. This proposal is what the young researcher will have as a starting point accompanied with the directive to publish. Add to this the scarcity of academic positions for young researchers and what you get is a machine to produce questionable “scientific” articles by design. But of course there is the peer review mechanism that is supposed to take care of this ! <strong><em>I refer the reader to our article on the peer review system</em></strong>.</p>

<p>It is difficult to classify any piece of work as useless unless said work has already been done or is clearly scientifically incorrect. Even tweaking the parameters of a machine learning model to produce different results could be deemed publishable if unexpected results are produced. And sharing of ideas is the way we collectively discover new concepts and incrementally build our understanding of new science. The problem might then originate from the subjectivity of what is deemed useful, interesting, incremental or useless. This is obvious to any researcher that has ever submitted an article for publication in a journal. Often reviewers will come to completely opposite conclusions as to the significance or validity of the work proposed. 
Is it a problem if a scientific article is published with errors? Or if the content of the article is not interesting to every reader? We would argue that the short answer to both questions is no, but of course it is not as simple. The full answer depends on the intentions of the authors when they wrote the article and those of the reviewers that let it get published. Did they genuinely think that the article had some value besides increasing their publication count and notoriety? Were they genuinely trying to solve a real problem besides justifying their funding? Were they helping a friend as they accepted the publication?
Publication count, notoriety and funding are the reality that we have to deal with but does it have to take precedence over the quality of the science we produce? Of course it shouldn’t but in reality this is what you do to survive, and it is easy to justify that it is just a means to an end. If you do not publish then you won’t secure enough funding to last you until your breakthrough, but a breakthrough often takes a long and hard focus that you cannot afford as you are chasing the next funding.  And imagine the danger of focusing on a hard problem for years and not reaching an answer, that would definitely kill your career. 
A logical conclusion to this is that researchers are paid (incentivised) to publish articles and not necessarily to advance our understanding of the world. This conclusion is arguably supported by the state of scientific literature today.</p>

<h2 id="research-in-industry">Research in industry</h2>
<p>It is interesting to compare what is happening in academia to the equivalent context in industry. Unlike academic research, industrial research is focused on solving specific problems which will bring value to the company in a relatively shorter time frame compared to academic research. This shift in incentives means that researchers in industry are focused on a specific goal that will ultimately be checked against the rigid constraints of the real world. In this environment, assessing the validity of the work is less of a subjective exercise, one only has to ask whether the original problem was solved. In this context also, writing an article without clear results does not make sense as the time  spent writing the article would be better valued working on a solution to the problem.
Of course the drawbacks here are that (1) there is an incentive to hide key elements of the work due to market competition (2) the research topics must often have a clear commercialisation path.
In a sense, academic research has become encumbered with short term incentives - by imposing a publish or perish mentality - whilst asking academic researchers to maintain a longer term vision. Those are two incompatible incentives that hinder scientific progress in the ways we have described.</p>

<h2 id="a-wider-societal-problem">A wider societal problem</h2>

<p>Most researchers start their career in academia knowing that their pay will not be as high as in industry but the drive to push the boundaries of science and have a shot at tackling the most challenging problems to mankind is too strong for them to resist and weighs higher in the balance. The reality they face is that quickly a tension begins to settle between normal life aspirations such as building a community, starting a family or providing stability to your family versus the precarity of academic employment. Most early career researchers are on temporary contracts and can remain in this situation for over a decade, it is expected that we change institutions, cities, even countries if we want to establish a career. At the same time faculties are reluctant to offer a permanent position to a young researcher as it is an expensive long term commitment for which they would have to take the risk of hiring an underperforming academic not able to help them achieve their target research output (mostly publications) and funding. Again, this is a logical behaviour from these faculties given their incentives to publish more and attract more funding. Nothing is said of the quality of life of their employees. This leads to researchers building strategies to improve their careers based on the number of published articles and funding secured with little emphasis on the quality of the work. The only way to increase those numbers is through short-term thinking incompatible with the scientific process.</p>

<p>Why is this a deeper societal issue ? Look around you and pay attention to the evolution of tastes over the course of your lifetime. Everything trends towards shorter timeframes and faster production and consumption with little consideration to our needs as humans. Often what gives is the quality of what is produced and consumed (fast food being the perfect example of this phenomenon). 
The irony is that researchers and engineers dedicate their lives to understanding the world and using that knowledge to build tools that will better our standard of living and free our time which in theory allows us in turn to worry less about survival and spend more time doing what we each deem more valuable to us. Instead the focus of our society is largely on economic growth at an exponential rate at the expense of quality of life, pushing prices up and leading everybody to optimise artificially their quantity of output at the expense of their quality. This is especially true for creative tasks that cannot yet be automated.
Interestingly the problem we have described in the scientific literature can be seen from the angle of a deeper societal problem:  The increasing cost of living.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-cope-with-literature">How to cope with literature?</h2>

<p>Given it will take an unknowable amount of time to change the fabric of our society to really address the problem at the core, one must find ways to cope in the meantime.</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Choose an extreme niche 
If you are in a position where you can choose your research project, make the best of this opportunity and pick something so niche that only a handful of people are working on the same problem, better yet create your own niche. This will make it much easier to track the progress of your area of expertise and searching through the literature will mostly mean looking for tools to help you solve a well defined problem. This will also give you focus as you develop your field and your expertise, slowly branching into new fields with your unique angle. 
The difficulty of this approach is that initially you might avoid the trendy topics that attract funding easily but if your chosen subject is of any importance your results will have value and you will find ways to branch into other more trendy fields - because everything in science is connected to something else if you look deeply enough. 
Of course you still need to identify a niche, which involves some understanding of the literature for things that people are not doing. The trap here is taking the shortcut of putting together a combination of hot topics in order to create a new discipline. Although this can lead to valuable results sometimes, one must really ask themselves what the end goal is. Is it curiosity driven or problem driven? Hopefully the goal is not just an additional paper.
Of course choosing a niche subject is a greater risk to take but this should arguably be the purpose of academic research; taking risks that are not commercially viable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ground yourself</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>You found yourself working on the latest trend that promises to turn any metal into gold, what do you do? Do you admit defeat faced with the tsunami of papers claiming to achieve just this?</p>

<p>This is often the case for young researchers that usually start their careers working on someone else’s project. Often, the principal investigator that proposed the project and obtained funding for it, has chosen a topic aligned with the thematic of big funding bodies. These thematics are where all researchers will flock to. The pro of this situation is that it creates an incentive for people to work on specific scientific issues but unfortunately also incentivises publishing of non-results from researchers with no real interest in the problem to solve.  <br />
If you find yourself in this case and happen to care about the topic of research, one thing you can do is build a prototype or experiment to represent the problem you are trying to solve. This is because in order to identify the work in the literature that will help you move forward you will need an anchor to reality. It is easy to get distracted by articles that pretend to solve your issue but starting from very wild assumptions. An experiment grounded in reality will serve as a filter to identify ideas that help you build forward.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Select journals and authors</li>
</ol>

<p>You found yourself working on the latest trend that promises to turn any metal into gold, but can’t build a prototype or experiment because it is too costly. 
If you are not in a position to build a prototype or experiment then you are probably in the worst of situations. This is usually the case where articles are written and published everyday with questionable and implicit assumptions, where many articles are written to solve trivial problems, results are applied without considering the conditions of validity of those results and there is no trivial way to know whether an article is worth reading without having read most of it. 
In this case a working strategy is to restrict the scope of your literature search to specialised and reputable journals  or to research groups known for their good work. Such strategy  reduces the variety of ideas you are exposed to and increases the likelihood of groupthink but it is arguably better than being exposed to an infinite pool of false or inconsequential results and having to sift through, especially as you are still building your expertise in the field.</p>

<p>Of course these three techniques are not mutually exclusive.</p>

<h2 id="concluding-remarks">Concluding remarks</h2>
<p>Researchers are increasingly building tools and curation systems to help them deal with the tsunami of articles coming their way, some of which can be found in these articles  <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nj7612-457a">Nature</a> and <a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/05/scientists-are-drowning-covid-19-papers-can-new-tools-keep-them-afloat">Science Magazine</a>. 
Ironically, the curation systems are also getting flooded, leading to more curation systems which in turn makes it difficult to navigate them… Back to square 1.</p>

<p>Hopefully this article has helped you understand the dynamics responsible for the degrading state of the scientific literature and has given you some tools to navigate it and grow as a researcher. 
If you have enjoyed this article or not, please leave us some feedback.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“The imposing edifice of science provides a challenging view of what can be achieved by the accumulation of many small efforts in a steady objective and dedicated search for truth” - Charles H. Townes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Enriching General Knowledge</title><link href="/2023/08/13/Enriching-General-Knowledge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enriching General Knowledge" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/Enriching-General-Knowledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/Enriching-General-Knowledge.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-general-knowledge-">What is general knowledge ?</h2>

<p>The ability to win pub quizzes every Thursday in a row for a month?
A definition of “general knowledge” from Oxford languages is - knowledge of a broad range of facts about various subjects. 
This definition is indeed close to what we usually mean by general knowledge but ignores a big part of it, which is “understanding” of the context or causality between those facts. It also doesn’t take into account knowledge as skill and experience. 
What we mean by knowledge in this article is all of the above.</p>

<p>The knowledge that we accumulate shapes our model of the world and how we interact with it. Additionally, the more information we collect about the world from as many angles as we can, the more accurately we can build our understanding of it.
The role of the researcher is to collect facts about the universe through experiments and build a coherent model to understand how things work at a fundamental level. With these models we can generate predictions that can be checked against reality or used to engineer more efficient systems.</p>

<p>The process of generating a model that matches the data at hand is a creative process but one that must be as objective as possible. However, being objective and creative at the same time is no easy task as creativity invites persona and cultural bias - for better or worse. An example of this bias is the Einstein cosmological constant that he removed from his field equation of general relativity as the general belief of the time favored a static universe; it was reintroduced after Hubble’s observations gave indisputable evidence for an expanding universe.
Removing the bias from their creative work is why researchers implement the scientific method: Observation -&gt; Hypothesis -&gt; Test -&gt; Refinement.  Despite this formal method, all those steps are also subjective to the researcher since like everybody else they will often only see what they are ready to see, formulate a hypothesis they are ready to accept, test what they believe is plausible and refine toward what fits their observation. This is not a bug of the scientific method but a feature because the diversity in biases is what leads to the exploration of multiple possible paths to arrive more quickly at the likely explanation of a phenomenon.
However, as an individual researcher, the ability to explore multiple possible theories, or in other words being creative, is an advantage to a successful career. The question is how does someone get more creative? The advice that is often given is to keep an open mind. But what does that mean in practice? Is it a passive task like sitting and waiting for new ideas to form whilst staring at the ceiling? Or something more active that requires active engagement of the brain? The answer I believe is, putting yourself in a position of being ready to see new patterns, make new connections and expand/change your beliefs and this is an active and continuous process.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-keep-an-open-mind">How to keep an open mind?</h2>

<p>An open mind requires curiosity, an active desire to explore alternative belief systems from the one we’re used to and more importantly to constantly question the robustness of our mental model of the world. In short, stepping out of one’s comfort zone. 
Due to the massive torrent of daily new research articles in every single field of research, it is natural to feel compelled to specialise in very narrow areas of science and become experts. This is needed to keep up with the pace and stand a chance to make a contribution to the field. However, that narrow focus, although it is great to build confidence in one’s abilities,  can be detrimental to the creativity and inspiration needed for breakthroughs. 
As a researcher, having a broad knowledge base extending beyond your field is a great asset. For example, tasked with the problem of designing a better air conditioning system for a building, a researcher can take inspiration from their knowledge of nature and  design a <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/130703-air-conditioning-biomimicry-natural-cooling">termite mound-influenced</a> design.  Like a novelist writing a story, the work of a researcher is fed by the diversity of his life experience with the difference in that the result of his work must meet the facts and constraints of reality.</p>

<h2 id="inspiration-is-found-in-diversity">Inspiration is found in diversity.</h2>

<p>The definition of inspiration from the Oxford Dictionary is “The process of being mentally stimulated to do or feel something, especially to do something creative”. Stimulation is external to a system, a stimulus in engineering is an input to a system that can trigger a reaction from it. For the creative brain of the researcher to be stimulated then requires external inputs.   It is therefore likely that the more diverse the interactions we have the more stimulated and inspired we are likely to be. Conversely, a still environment can be negative to the formation of new ideas and can lead to lack of inspiration and <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/bitesize/articles/zvyhpg8">motivation</a>. Of course there is a nuance to this argument as the maturation of ideas also requires a level of stillness and long uninterrupted thoughts.</p>

<h2 id="how-do-you-stay-inspired-creative-and-motivated">How do you stay inspired, creative and motivated?</h2>

<p>Luckily, if you are a researcher, it means somewhere in you there is a blackhole that feasts on knowledge. Unleash it ! Now that we have established that the success of your job as a researcher depends on you being exposed to new ideas, take it as an excuse to learn as much as you can. For example:
Learn a new language. Languages are condensed information about a foreign culture, a different vision of the world than yours, nothing is better than having a diversity of angles to look at the world if you want to build a better understanding of it.
Engage with people outside your community and preferably with different beliefs than your own.
Travel to countries with customs different to yours.<br />
Read books and listen to podcasts outside your field of expertise.
Take dance lessons if you don’t know how to dance.
Learn to play an instrument.
The choice is yours…</p>

<p>Get out of your comfort zone and into the unknown and not only in your narrow field of research because no one knows where your next breakthrough will come from. You might find the answers you are looking for in the next cake  you learn to bake..</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is general knowledge ?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Relax</title><link href="/2023/08/13/Relax.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relax" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/Relax</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/Relax.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-importance-of-relaxing-as-a-researcher-">The importance of relaxing as a researcher !</h2>

<p>We have all heard the story of Newton seeing an apple falling from a tree whilst daydreaming which lead him to unlock the secrets of gravity or the story of Archimedes running out of his bath naked and shouting eureka as he figured out a way to measure the volume of irregular objects seeing how his immersed body displaced his bath water. Whether these stories really did happen or whether they are legends we cannot know for sure, but one thing they hint at is that scientific discoveries do not just happen through active thoughts and relentless scribbling on a sheet of paper or on a blackboard. They happen also and maybe even more so when the scientist is in a relaxed state of mind and gives enough time to their thoughts to fully mature.</p>

<p>As you would expect, the job of a researcher is highly intellectual and demands periods of deep focus in order to connect together different clues and arrive at a coherent model of the problem at hand and hopefully a way toward a solution. High levels of stress are not conducive to the best results. Of course this is true for other types of activities too but when it is your mind that is your main tool for the job, stress and fatigue are your main enemies. For the modern researcher, sources of stress and fatigue abound ! 
Living in the digital age means having limitless sources of stress in the form of overstimulation by apps that all beg for your attention and algorithms that are trained to better activate your dopamine receptors and keep you connected at all times. As a victim of these algorithms myself, I often wonder if there could ever be a worse weapon against researchers than one that promises to hit them with new information everytime they refresh the page. This might actually be an evil plot against us! Is there a way out of this ? None that doesn’t involve putting down your devices and enjoying a bit of silence, all alone with your thoughts. Ideally you may want to take on an activity that is mechanical and repetitive, one that allows you to escape your body for a few moments like knitting, walking, running, painting… 
Another major disruption to the peace needed for our noble goal of advancing the frontiers of knowledge is the gargantuan amount of tasks given to researchers and that we detail here on Researcharium. Indeed, between preparing lectures, marking assignments, reviewing articles, hiring, mentoring, teaching, writing proposals and so on, it becomes very difficult to have the time to just relax and free our minds for new ideas to form. The best advice is to find a way to become a master of time management. At the very least, be aware of the amount of work you need to do and schedule time to relax and play with ideas. It is best to have these slots marked down in your calendar to avoid having something compete for your attention then. 
Besides the beneficial impact on your activities as a researcher, taking the time to relax is also good for your mental and physical health. So go carve out some time to do nothing but relax! You are a researcher.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The importance of relaxing as a researcher !]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Stresses Of The Digital Age</title><link href="/2023/08/13/The-Stresses-Of-The-Digital-Age.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stresses Of The Digital Age" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/The-Stresses-Of-The-Digital-Age</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/The-Stresses-Of-The-Digital-Age.html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you also noticed your attention span decrease drastically? Well you are not alone…</p>

<p>The information age has given us the ability to access entire libraries in a blink of an eye and at the same time enabled new behaviors such as doom scrolling the news feeds of various apps hoping to find new gems whilst lead astray by AI systems that completely hijacked our brain’s reward system to keep us captivated and harvest our attention for ad revenue. As attention became a currency it seems we lost the ability to pay attention. In this context, how are the current and next generation of researchers ever going to collect their thoughts long enough to formulate the next revolutionary shift in paradigm? Send me a tweet if you figure this out…
I guess the answer is easy, put down your devices! Easily said than done, especially when you need them for your research. You are always only one click away from a dopamine hit, how to resist?
One trick that seems to work for me is setting aside time for scrolling social media or perusing the internet. With this I’ll get my ground breaking discovery anytime now !</p>

<h2 id="the-academic-pressure">The academic pressure</h2>

<p>Contrary to what some people think, researchers are not mostly sitting in their offices thinking about ideas all day. If it was the case, I for one would not complain about it as this is fundamentally their job. Maybe that used to be the case in some past utopic era and then, being jealous, the rest of the world conspired to add useless tasks to the researcher’s role. This is an exaggeration, however, when you hear the former president of France Nicolas Sarkozy say that British researchers are publishing more whilst French ones are using light and heating (I am paraphrasing) you know someone is ready to pull the rug from under you if you happen to be a researcher in France.
Research is not an activity that can be assessed on the same basis as engineering, as a researcher you are inventing the way to think about things no one has ever thought about. Of course you might not succeed for a while and this is a risk society should be willing to take as  we are probing the unknown. Moreover, it takes time to digest and formulate a clear understanding of something at the edge of human knowledge. Assessing researchers on some deterministic metric might not be the best approach and trying to get your money’s worth of work by adding additional responsibilities onto them is counter productive. All that is achieved is increased levels of stress and lower levels of productivity. But of course if the funding needs to be justified based on the number of publications then one can always publish immature ideas and get an extra month of heating covered.
The solution to this issue is more structural and probably also deeply social. We discuss this in some ways in our blog post coping with literature.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Have you also noticed your attention span decrease drastically? Well you are not alone…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Peer Reviewing Papers</title><link href="/2023/08/13/Peer-reviewing-papers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Peer Reviewing Papers" /><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/08/13/Peer-reviewing-papers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/13/Peer-reviewing-papers.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="on-peer-reviewing-papers">On peer-reviewing papers</h1>

<p>They have been sitting on our desk for several weeks. In the corner, just over there. We know that they are waiting for us. Reminders keep popping in the mailbox: the deadline is coming soon. That’s the same story every time. We know we want to have them done on time. We know it is a matter of priorities. We know we decided to be more proactive. And yet, two days to go and there are five of them waiting to be scrutinised. We will have to block the day tomorrow to work on our paper reviews.
In the pool of all our research activities, to peer-review papers is one of these background tasks for which we often demonstrate ambivalent feelings.
Having knowledge progress keeps us eager to pursue our research journey. After all it is pretty exciting to participate in the construction of a research that moves forwards through the confrontation of ideas. At the same time we know that peer-reviewing (whether a paper, some codes, or a dataset, etc.) is something time-consuming that can rapidly turn overwhelming.
So where should we draw a line?
The article shares some thoughts on how we may want to engage more effectively in this task. For the sake of clarity, the article focuses on the case of paper peer-review.</p>
<h2 id="paper-peer-review-whats-that">Paper peer-review, what’s that?</h2>
<p>Research is a lot about communicating. Communication is essential to share ideas and perspectives, and keep an open mind on our own work.
The traditional way to communicate in research is through the publication of so-called papers.
Papers are (highly) specialised written pieces of work. They typically take the form of articles that follow a set of field-specific rules. On one hand, the rules define the nature and type of content in the paper. For instance, the paper can be a presentation of an initial idea about a problem, e.g., there is potential in using technology X to reduce the energy needed to operate a datacentre and here are the arguments why. It can also be the report of a fully-fleshed solution to a specific problem, e.g., we use technology X to create a system that reduces the energy cost by Y% when operating a datacentre and that is easy to deploy. On the other hand, the rules dictate editorial constraints. For instance papers often come with a length limit, either in terms of number of words or number of pages.
Papers are made available to the interested audience as published articles by specialised publishers. Publishers are just the end point of a long process orchestrated by peers in the research community. The goal of this process is to decide whether a paper should be accepted for publication or not, and this decision is taken as the result of a peer-review phase.
Peer-review consists in soliciting, for a paper, the community of contributors of a relevant field of knowledge with interests, experience and/or expertise related to the focus of the paper. The objective is to get an informed view from the community on the quality of the reported work. Quality is in essence a broad term that covers rigour (e.g., the findings are evidence-based, the construction of ideas follows a valid methodology, etc.); novelty (i.e., the paper reports something that contributes to enriching knowledge); as well as presentation and expression (i.e., the paper can be read – a non-negligeable aspect…).
In practise peer-review is an efficient way to foster the validation and exchange of ideas. It helps better shape our understanding of a problem. It has however a crucial facet: it operates on a benevolent basis. In other words, there are no financial incentives for participating in a peer-review process.
Peer-reviewers are thus facing a paradoxical situation. We are on one hand happy to get involved in the construction of an healthy research. On the other hand, we are trapped in a mechanism that capitalises on de facto altruism to sustain an ecosystem that treats as a (free) service the enrichment of knowledge.
We therefore need to set limits to ourself and to the rest of the community on what we can decently agree to commit.</p>
<h2 id="to-accept-a-review-or-not">To accept a review or not?</h2>
<p>It might be trivial but it is nevertheless important to decide upon receiving a solicitation for review if we should accept it or not.
Let’s make it clear. It takes time (and efforts) to do a good review. It does take time. The job includes 1) critically reading the work of others and understanding if their arguments make sense; and 2) formulating constructive feedback and synthetising some remarks in a clear and structured way. We should not forget that the end goal (from researchers’ eyes) is to help peers (aka. the authors of the paper in this case) to correct any potential weaknesses. The ability to read an often complex piece of work while keeping an open and yet critical mind, and putting in words meaningful recommendations, is not something that can be ditched in two minutes.
So before being highly enthusiastic about the idea of helping the community, it seems to be reasonable to spend a bit of time on deciding whether we should accept a review invitation.
To accept a review comes with some responsibilities. Can we honestly do a good job? The reviews we provide should be the reviews we would like to receive. If there is a chance we will not be able to commit more than a few minutes to do a good job, let’s just be honest, and decline.
There is besides no point in accepting to review a paper dealing with a topic for which we have rather limited knowledge. We are not only unlikely to provide any meaningful feedback, we are also prone to rapidly feel discouraged and unable to complete the review on time. 
Reviews are just one step in the long process of publication. When committing to provide a review, we should remember that any delay in returning our assessment can have an impact on the rest of the process. In particular this can constitute extra workload for the people involved in collecting and orchestrating these reviews (<strong>see organising an event</strong>) who would need to chase after late-returners to get everything ready.<br />
It just takes a few minutes of our time to be realistic about our current workload and capability. There is no harm in saying no to an invitation.</p>
<h2 id="the-art-of-delegation">The art of delegation</h2>
<p>Every community has an ageing factor. The longer one in, the more exposed one becomes. As we grow in maturity in our field of research, we tend to receive more invitations to peer-review papers. <br />
The ability to provide good reviews comes with experience. As such it is definitely a good practise for “young” researchers to be trained to develop critical thinking and to produce constructive, synthetic, feedback. In that respect there is clear value in delegating a review to a less experienced colleague.
However, delegation is not necessarily a straightforward thing, especially in the context of peer-review where there is responsibility engaged.
If the review is delegated to a less experienced researcher, it is essential to ensure that the person has the competence to work on it independently. If not, we have the responsibility to provide guidance, and keep an eye on the final version of the review text. This aspect should be factored in.<br />
If the review is delegated to a peer (same or higher level of experience) or independent researcher, it is important to trust the delegee can do a good job. After all, given that the invitation first came to us, it seems wise to redirect it to someone we believe could have been contacted in the first place.
In either case, it should be systematic for the person who did the review to be directly credited. We know that doing a good review requires skills, efforts and time. It is therefore logical to have the person recognised for the work done. More musings about being credited below.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-rate-our-expertise">How to rate our expertise?</h2>
<p>It is evident that our ability to review a paper very much depends on how comfortable we feel with the reviewed topic.
Let’s take a paper and look at the range of reviews the work received. There is a high chance of overlaps between the comments from different reviewers. At the same time it is also very likely that the paper got a diversity of views. By soliciting a pool of reviewers, different aspects of the work can be scrutinised. 
While each review bears its significance, it is sensible for the different points of view to be weighted based on how confident a reviewer feels with respect to the topic. A very confident reviewer has the ability to evaluate a paper in depth, while a reviewer with limited knowledge on a topic is less likely to be able to comment on the novelty of an idea for instance. 
The issue is that it is typically up to the reviewer to self-assess her/his level of expertise on a topic (ranging from novice to expert, through limited knowledge and knowledgeable – or derivatives of these broad qualifiers). This practise is in design subjective since a number of factors can directly impact how one is likely to rate her/his competence.
There are of course safeguards to limit biases in self-assessment. The most obvious one is to solicit a diverse pool of reviewers. Another is to introduce a discussion phase among reviewers, which can give a chance to everyone to rethink the initial assessment. Another level of control can come from the committee who coordinates the reviews and is responsible for making the final decision.  <br />
Different research communities are likely to implement different methods of expertise assessment. The bottom line is that as reviewers, we should do our best to strike the right balance between being highly confident and too timid with respect to the experience we have already acquired.</p>
<h2 id="a-matter-of-respect">A matter of respect</h2>
<p>The objective of peer-review is to help everyone getting feedback on their work. It helps sanitising the development of ideas by confronting point of views and perspectives.
It is in our ethos of researchers to contribute to enriching knowledge. Our perspectives can be different. Our ideas can be contradictory. Our thinking can be wrong. Reviews are an opportunity to make things better. In that regard let’s respect each other’s time and efforts.<br />
As reviewers we have in our hand the result of week(s)/month(s)/maybe year(s) of work. We may not believe that the paper is good enough. We may think that it has too many weaknesses. Whatever its quality, we need to remember that people put time and efforts in creating something. We should be respectful of this work and 1) provide feedback that is relevant, 2) present the comments in a decent form (it is easy to write a sentence), and 3) have the diligence to do our best to understand the paper.
We, reviewers, do our job in a benevolent fashion. We take on our time to help others. So it can be highly irritating to keep receiving daily reminders about the deadline for reviews coming soon. Reminders are good as long as they do not become intrusive.
Another point of the utmost disrespect is to close the submission of reviews before the initially communicated deadline. If we are given a deadline, we have by definition up to that deadline to return the review. It is highly impolite to solicit someone and not wait for the person’s feedback.
Finally it may sound rather obvious but it is disrespectful to discard someone else’s opinion. Again research is about confrontation of point of views. Reviews realise part of this vision.</p>
<h2 id="what-about-being-credited">What about being credited?</h2>
<p>Research can have this tendency towards over-emphasising what is good for personal development. It seems easy to forget that being a researcher is a job. As a job, it does matter to be rewarded for what we do (and not necessarily for our personal gratification).
In the outside world, people can call themselves food critics, film journalists, novel critics, etc. The essence of their job is to review others’ work.<br />
Reviews are central to how research operates today. But there is a limit on us contributors in the system being best-effort based, whether in terms of number of solicitations, workload associated with each invitation, or imposed timeline.
Again peer-reviewing a paper necessitates specific skills, time and efforts. We need a system that can concretely reward our contributions. It is somehow agreed that researchers have to participate in peer-review activities. That’s fair enough but is this valued from outside the small circle of our solicitors? Yes, a thank you is nice but an accumulation of thank you is after all just a thank you. Tell me if I am wrong but no one would buy much in this world with a thank you.
Some systems have been developed in the recent years to give a formal recognition for the reviews we do (see for instance publons https://publons.com/about/home/). It remains however unclear how these systems can be used as validators of competence within and outside the research arena.</p>
<h1 id="a-short-conclusion">A short conclusion</h1>
<p>Paper peer-review forms an ecosystem in the ecosystem of XXIst century research. Relying on volunteering and self-engagement for supporting this system going is however questionable. In a time where sustaining a research career has become challenging, we collectively need to have an open discussion on the role and mechanisms of reviews.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On peer-reviewing papers]]></summary></entry></feed>